<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>R on Josiah Parry</title>
    <link>/categories/r/</link>
    <description>Recent content in R on Josiah Parry</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/categories/r/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>[Not so] generic functions</title>
      <link>/post/function-methods/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/function-methods/</guid>
      <description>The Jargon The Generic Method The Default Method sf method tbl_graph method Review (tl;dr)   Lately I have been doing more of my spatial analysis work in R with the help of the sf package. One shapefile I was working with had some horrendously named columns, and naturally, I tried to clean them using the clean_names() function from the janitor package. But lo, an egregious error occured. To this end, I officially filed my complaint as an issue.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Chunking your csv</title>
      <link>/post/write-chunked-csv/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/write-chunked-csv/</guid>
      <description>Sometimes due to limitations of software, file uploads often have a row limit. I recently encountered this while creating texting campaigns using Relay. Relay is a peer-to-peer texting platform. It has a limitation of 20k contacts per texting campaign. This is a limitation when running a massive Get Out the Vote (GOTV) texting initiative.
In order to solve this problem, a large csv must be split into multiple csv’s for upload.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reading Multiple csvs as 1 data frame</title>
      <link>/post/read-chunked-csv/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/read-chunked-csv/</guid>
      <description>In an earlier posting I wrote about having to break a single csv into multiple csvs. In other scenarios one data set maybe provided as multiple a csvs.
Thankfully purrr has a beautiful function called map_df() which will make this into a two liner. This process has essentially 3 steps.
Create a vector of all .csv files that should be merged together. Read each file using readr::read_csv() Combine each dataframe into one.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Coursera R-Programming: Week 2 Problems</title>
      <link>/post/tidy-coursera-r-programming/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/tidy-coursera-r-programming/</guid>
      <description>Over the past several weeks I have been helping students, career professionals, and people of other backgrounds learn R. During this time one this has become apparent, people are teaching the old paradigm of R and avoiding the tidyverse all together.
I recently had a student reach out to me in need of help with the first programming assignment from the Coursera R-Programming course (part of the Johns Hopkins Data Science Specialization).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introducing geniusR</title>
      <link>/post/introducing-geniusr/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/introducing-geniusr/</guid>
      <description>Introducing geniusR geniusR enables quick and easy download of song lyrics. The intent behind the package is to be able to perform text based analyses on songs in a tidy[text] format.
This package was inspired by the release of Kendrick Lamar’s most recent album, DAMN.. As most programmers do, I spent way too long to simplify a task, that being accessing song lyrics. Genius (formerly Rap Genius) is the most widly accessible platform for lyrics.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>